so let's look at an example of how a
right back cache would work say we have
a small for entry cache that is direct
map each line has a valid bit a tag and
a dirty bit we don't need the lru
counter because in a direct map cache we
know exactly what to replace we don't
need L counters to tell us that let's
say that the processor is doing this
sequence of accesses and a b and c map
to different sets in the cache the first
ACC is Right a so what we do is we have
a miss all of our valid bits are zero so
it doesn't matter what the rest of the
cache has because none of the lines are
valid when we have the first right to a
we will bring a here we will change the
valid bit to one and we would change the
tag to correspond to a because this is a
right the processor as soon as the data
is brought in will write it and the
Dirty Bit will be set to one next we
have a read to a the processor checks
the tag and the valid bit sees that the
tag match is a and the valid bit is one
so it can just use a the fact that the
Dirty Bit is one doesn't change anything
next let's say we have a read B we don't
find anything that matches B in the
cache or maybe if this does the valid
bit is zero so it doesn't matter so we
will have a miss and bring B into the
cache change the tag to correspond to B
change the valid bit to one to indicate
that we do have something here now and
because this is only a read the Dirty
Bit will be zero next let's say we read
C it's a Miss bring C in change the tag
on the valid bit it's a read so the
Dirty Bit starts out at zero next what
we have is a right to see we check if
it's a hit and it is we write only to
the cache and change the Dirty Bit to
one and now as you can see the Dirty Bit
for every line indicates simply was the
line ever written since it was last
brought into the cache let's continue
this by an access to e that is a read
and let's say that e Maps where a is so
now what needs to happen is we're going
to check here to see whether the tag
matches e it doesn't so we have a miss
our replacement policy is simple for
direct map caches we simply replace
whatever is there so at this point we
cannot just bring in E from memory first
we have to take the data for a that we
have written and not written to memory
yet because the Dirty Bit is one this
block gets sent to memory as a right
after that happens we can bring e in set
the tag and valid bit and the Dirty Bit
to zero because it's a read and this
continues on let's say that now we have
a read to F which replaces B when we
want to replace B we check the Dirty Bit
it's zero so B doesn't get sent to
memory it simply gets overwritten with
the data from F we Fetch and because
this is a read we get a zero here and so
on